<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
     <string name="source_link">
        Source:
         <a href="http://www.knowledgebank.irri.org/step-by-step-production/growth/pests-and-diseases/insects">
            www.knowledgebank.irri.org.
         </a>
    </string>
    -------------------------------------------------<!--Brown Planthopper-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="bph_name">Brown Planthopper</string>
    <string name="bph_sci_name">Nilaparvata lugens</string>
    <string name="bph_does">
        High population of planthoppers cause leaves to initially turn orange-yellow before becoming brown and dry and this is a
        condition called hopperburn that kills the plant.
        \n
        \nBPH can also transmit Rice Ragged Stunt and Rice Grassy Stunt diseases. Neither disease can be cured.
    </string>
    <string name="bph_why_where">
       Planthoppers can be a problem in rainfed and in irrigated wetland environments. It also occurs in areas with continuous submerged
        conditions in the field, high shade, and humidity.
        \n
        \nClosed canopy of the rice plants, densely seeded crops, excessive use of nitrogen, and early season insecticide spraying also favors insect development.
    </string>
    <string name="bph_identify">
        Check for the presence of insect:
        \n
        \n-crescent-shaped white eggs inserted into the midrib or leaf sheath
        \n-white to brown nymphs
        \n-brown or white adults feeding near the base of tillers
        \n
        \nCheck the field for:
        \n
        \n-hopperburn or yellowing, browning and drying of plant
        \n-ovipositional marks exposing the plant to fungal and bacterial infections
        \n-presence of honeydew and sooty molds in the bases of areas infected
        \n-plants with ragged stunt or grassy stunt virus disease
        \n
        \nHopperburn is similar to the feeding damage or "bugburn" caused by the rice black bug. To confirm hopperburn caused by planthoppers,
        check for the presence of sooty molds at the base of the plant.
    </string>
    <string name="bph_pesticide">
        PHENOM 50 EC
        \nPHENDEX 350 EC
        \nDISCOVERY 5 EC
    </string>
    <string name="bph_active_ing">
        PHENTHOATE
      \nPHENTHOATE+BPMC
       \nCYPERMETHRIN
    </string>

    <string name="bph_important">
        The feeding damage caused by planthoppers results in the yellowing of the plants. At high population density, hopperburn or complete
        drying of the plants is observed. At this level, crop loss may be 100%.
        \n
        \nIn field conditions, plants nearing maturity can have hopperburns if infested with about 400−500 BPH nymphs. In the 1970s and 1980s,
        BPH was considered a threat to rice production in Asia. BPH also transmit Rice Ragged Stunt and Rice Grassy Stunt viruses..
        \n
        \nAt a population density of 400−500 nymphs or 200 adults per plant, WBPH can cause complete loss of rice plants. Outbreaks of WBPH were
        reported in Pakistan in 1978, Malaysia in 1979, and India in 1982, 1984, and 1985.
    </string>
    <string name="bph_mngmnt">
        Outbreaks result from pesticides destroying natural enemies (BPH eggs hatch unchecked, and surviving BPH quickly build-up populations to
            damaging levels), or when longwinged planthoppers are being carried in by the wind.
        \n
        \nTo prevent outbreaks of planthopper:
        \n
        \n1. Remove weeds from the field and surrounding areas.
        \n2. Avoid indiscriminate use of insecticide, which destroys natural enemies.
        \n3. Use a resistant variety. Contact your local agriculture office for an up-to-date list of available varieties.
        \n4. Critical numbers: At a density of 1 BPH/stem or less there is still time to act in case the numbers increase.
        \n5. Look for BPH daily in the seedbed, or weekly in the field, on stems and the water surface. Check each side of
            the seed bed (or direct-seeded fields). For older rice plants, grasp the plant, bend it over slightly, and gently
            tap it near the base to see if planthoppers fall onto the water surface. For transplanted rice look at bases of 10
            to 20 hills as you cross the field diagonally. There is no need to scout for BPH or WBPH beyond the milk stage.
        \n6. Use light traps (e.g., an electric bulb or kerosene lamp near a light colored wall or over a pan of water) at night
            when rice is prone to planthopper attack. Do not place lights near seedbeds or fields. If the light trap is inundated
            with hundreds of BPH, it\'s a signal to check your seedbed or field immediately; then scout every day for the next few weeks.
            If farmers monitor on a daily basis anyway, then a light trap is unnecessary.
        \n
        \nTo control planthoppers:
        \n
        \nMechanical &amp; physical measures
        \n
        \n-Flood the seedbed, for a day, so that only the tips of seedlings are exposed will control BPH.
        \n-Sweep small seedbeds with a net to remove some BPH (but not eggs), particularly from dry seed beds. At high BPH densities,
            sweeping will not remove sufficient numbers of BPH from the base of the plant.
        \n
        \nBiological control
        \n
        \n-If natural enemies out-number BPH the risk of hopperburn is low. Even rice already damaged by hopperburn should
            not be treated with insecticides if natural enemies out-number BPH. Natural enemies of BPH include water striders,
            mirid bugs, spiders, and various egg parasitoids.
        \n
        \nChemical control
        \n
        \nOnly apply insecticides to the seedbed, for BPH or WBPH, if all of these conditions are met:
        \n
        \n-an average of more than one planthopper per stem,
        \n-on average, more planthoppers than natural enemies,
        \n-flooding the seedbed is not an option.
        \n
    </string>
    <string name="bph_hyperlink">
        Source:
        <a href="http://www.knowledgebank.irri.org/training/fact-sheets/pest-management/insects/item/planthopper">
            knowledgebank.irri.org
        </a>
    </string>
-------------------------------------------------<!--Green Leaf Hopper-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="glh_name">Green Planthopper</string>
    <string name="glh_sci_name">Nephotettix virescens</string>
    <string name="glh_does">
       Green leafhoppers are the most common leafhoppers in rice fields and are primarily critical because they spread the viral disease tungro.
        Both nymphs and adults feed by extracting plant sap with their needle-shaped mouthparts.
    </string>
    <string name="glh_why_where">
        Staggered planting encourages population growth of GLH.
        \n
        \nGreen leafhoppers are common in rainfed and irrigated wetland environments. They are not prevalent in upland rice.
            Both the nymphs and adults feed on the dorsal surface of the leaf blades rather than the ventral surface. They prefer to feed on
            the lateral leaves rather than the leaf sheaths and the middle leaves. They also prefer rice plants that have been fertilized with large amount of nitrogen.
    </string>
    <string name="glh_important">
        Green leafhoppers are important pests. They are vectors of viral diseases such as tungro, yellow dwarf, yellow-orange leaf, transitory yellowing, and dwarf.
    </string>
    <string name="glh_identify">
        Rice fields infested by GLH can have tungro, yellow dwarf, yellow-orange leaf, and transitory yellowing diseases.
        \n
        \nSymptoms include:
        \n
        \n-stunted plants and reduced vigor
        \nreduced number of productive tillers
        \n-withering or complete plant drying
        \n
        \nTungro infected crops may sometimes be confused with nitrogen deficiency or iron toxicity or acid soils.
        To confirm the cause of the problem, check for virus infected plants in the fields, and the presence of the insect:
        \n
        \n-white or pale yellow eggs inside leaf sheaths or midribs
        \nyellow or pale green nymphs with or without black markings
        \npale green adults with or without black markings feeding on upper parts of the crop
    </string>
    <string name="glh_pesticide">
        LAMDAXIN 2.5 EC \nAGRO CYPERMETHRIN 5 EC \nPHENOM 50 EC
    </string>
    <string name="glh_active_ing">
       LAMBDA‐CYHALOTHRIN \nCYPERMETHRIN  \nPHENTHOATE
    </string>

    <string name="glh_mngmnt">
        1. Use GLH-resistant and tungro-resistant varieties. Contact your local agriculture office for an up-to-date list of available varieties.
        \n2. Reduce the number of rice crops to two per year and synchronized crop establishment across farms reduces leafhoppers and other insect vectors.
        \n3. Transplant older seedlings (>3 weeks) to reduce viral disease susceptibility transmitted by leafhoppers.
        \n4. Plant early within a given planting period, particularly in the dry season to reduce the risk of insect-vector disease.
        \n5. Avoid planting during the peak of GLH activity (shown by historical records) to avoid infestation. Light traps can be used to show GLH numbers.
        \n6. Apply nitrogen as needed (e.g., using the Leaf Color Chart) to avoid contributing to population outbreaks by applying too much nitrogen, or hindering
            plant recovery from planthopper damage by applying insufficient nitrogen.
        \n7. Control weeds in the field and on the bunds to remove the preferred grassy hosts of GLH and promotes crop vigor.
        \n8. Perform crop rotation with a non-rice crop during the dry season to decrease alternate hosts for diseases.
        \n9. Intercrop upland rice with soybean to reduce the incidence of leafhoppers on rice.
        \n
        \nIn areas without tungro source, insecticides are not needed, avoid spraying of insecticide (it is often unable to prevent or reduce tungro infections).
        \n
        \nEncourage biological control agents: small wasps (parasitize the eggs), mirid bug; strepsipterans, small wasps, pipunculid flies, and nematodes (parasitize
            both the nymphs and adults), aquatic veliid bugs, nabid bugs, empid flies, damselflies, dragonflies, and spiders, fungal pathogen (attacks both nymph
        and adult).
    </string>
    <string name="glh_hyperlink">
        Source:
        <a href="http://www.knowledgebank.irri.org/training/fact-sheets/pest-management/insects">
                    knowledgebank.irri.org
        </a>
    </string>
 -------------------------------------------------<!--Rice Bug-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="rb_name">Rice Bug</string>
    <string name="rb_sci_name">Leptocorisa acuta</string>
    <string name="rb_does">
            Rice bugs damage rice by sucking out the contents of developing grains from pre-flowering spikelets to soft dough stage,
        therefore causing unfilled or empty grains and discoloration. Immature and adult rice bugs both feed on rice grains.
    </string>
    <string name="rb_why_where">
        High rice bug populations are brought about by factors such as nearby woodlands, extensive weedy areas near rice fields, wild grasses near canals,
        and staggered rice planting. The insect also becomes active when the monsoonal rains begin. Warm weather, overcast skies, and frequent drizzles favor
        its population buildup.
        \n
        \nThe population of the rice bug increases at the end of the rainy season.
        \n
        \nRice bugs are found in all rice environments. They are more common in rainfed and upland rice and prefer the flowering to milky stages of the rice crop.
        \n
        \nAdults are active during the late afternoon and early morning. Under bright sunlight, they hide in grassy areas.
        They are less active during the dry season. In cooler areas, the adults undergo a prolonged development in grasses.
        They feed on wild hosts for one to two generations before migrating into the rice fields at the flowering stages.
        The nymphs are found on the rice plant where they blend with the foliage. There, they are often left unnoticed.
        When disturbed, the nymphs drop to the lower part of the plants and the adults fly within a short distance.
    </string>
    <string name="rb_identify">
        Check the plant for feeding damage, such as
        \n
        \n-small or shriveled grains,
        \n-deformed or spotty grains,
        \n-empty grains, and
        \n-erect panicles.
        \n
        \nThe symptoms can be confused with the damage caused by nutrient deficiency or flower thrips.
        To confirm rice bug infestation, check for presence of insect:
        \n
        \noval, shiny, and reddish brown eggs along midrib of leaf
        \nslender and brown-green nymphs and adults feeding on endosperm of rice grains
        \noffensive smell
    </string>
    <string name="rb_important">
        Both the adults and nymphs feed on grains at the milking stage. They can be serious pests of rice and sometimes reduce yield by as much as 30%.
    </string>
    <string name="rb_pesticide">LAMDAXIN 2.5 EC \nTRUGOLD 60 EC \nSUPERSMAK 50 EC</string>
    <string name="rb_active_ing">LAMBDA-CYHALOTHRIN 25 g/L \nDIAZINON 600 g/L \nN CYPERMETHRIn 50g/L</string>
    <string name="rb_mngmnt">
        1. Remove weeds from fields and surrounding areas to prevent the multiplication of rice bugs during fallow periods.
        \n2. Level fields with even applications of fertilizer and water encourage rice to grow and develop is at the same rate.
        Planting fields, within a village, at the same time (synchronous planting) also helps reduce rice bug problems.
        \n3. Capturing rice bugs, in the early morning or late afternoon, by net can be effective at low rice bug densities, though labor intensive.
        \n4. Encourage biological control agents: Some wasps, grasshoppers and spiders attack rice bugs or rice bug eggs.
        Indiscriminate insecticide use disrupts biological control, resulting in pest resurgence.
        \n
        \n5. For chemical control
        \n
        \nBefore using a pesticide contact a crop protection specialist for suggestions, guidance, and warnings specific to your situation.
        \n
        \n1. Begin scouting the field at pre-flowering and continue daily until the hard dough stage.
        Count rice bugs in the early morning or late afternoon from 20 hills while walking diagonally across a transplanted field.
        Adults often fly out of the way before you reach the rice plant, so counts may only reveal immature forms.
        Direct control may be required if there are more than 10 rice bugs/20 hills.
        \n2. The choice of insecticide depends on many factors such as the application equipment available,
        cost of the insecticide, experience of the applicator, or presence of fish. The benefits of using an
        insecticide must be weighed against the risks to health and the environment.
    </string>
    <string name="rb_hyperlink">
        Source:
        <a href="http://www.knowledgebank.irri.org/training/fact-sheets/pest-management/insects/item/rice-bug">
            knowledgebank.irri.org
        </a>
    </string>
    -------------------------------------------------<!--Rice Black Bug-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="rbb_name">Rice Black Bug</string>
    <string name="rbb_sci_name">Scotinophara coarctata</string>
    <string name="rbb_does">
        Black bugs remove the sap of the plant. They can cause browning of leaves, deadheart, and bugburn.
        Their damage also causes stunting in plants, reduced tiller number, and formation of whiteheads.
        \n
        \nOn severe cases, black bugs weaken the plant preventing them from producing seeds.
    </string>
    <string name="rbb_why_where">
        The insect is common in rainfed and irrigated wetland environments. It prefers continuously cropped
        irrigated rice areas and poorly drained fields. Damages are observed more frequently in dry season rice crops and densely planted fields.
        \n
        \nBlack bug flight patterns are affected by the lunar cycle; on full moon nights, large numbers of adults swarm to light sources.
        \n
        \nStaggered planting of the rice crop and excessive nitrogen also favor the buildup of the pest. During non-rice periods,
        the presence of alternate breeding site favors population increase.
    </string>
    <string name="rbb_identify">
        1. Check leaves for discoloration. Black bug damage can cause reddish brown or yellowing of plants. Leaves also have chlorotic lesions.
      \n2. Check for decreased tillering. Bugburn symptoms show wilting of tillers with no visible honeydew deposits or sooty molds.
      \n3. Plants are also stunted; and can develop stunted panicles, no panicles, incompletely exerted panicles, and unfilled spikelets
        or whiteheads at booting stage.
      \n4. Check for deadhearts.
      \n
      \n Deadhearts can also be caused by stemborer. To confirm cause of damage, pull infected plants. In black bug damage,
        infected plants cannot be pulled at the bases.
      \n
      \n Heavy infestation and "bugburn" is usually visible after heading or maturing.
    </string>
    <string name="rbb_important">
        Black bug feeds on the rice plant from seedling to maturity growth stages. Ten black bug adults per hill can cause losses of up to 35% in some rice.
    </string>
    <string name="rbb_pesticide">
        NIMBECIDINE
        \nCHIX 2.5 EC
        \nDECIS 2.5 EC
    </string>
    <string name="rbb_active_ing">
        DELTAMETHRIN 25 g/L
        \nBETA-CYPERMETHRIN 25 g/L
        \nAZADIRACHTIN 3g/L
    </string>
    <string name="rbb_mngmnt">
        Integrated Management of Rice Black Bug
        \n
        \nTo prevent black bug infestation:
        \n1. Use resistant varieties.
        \n   1.1 Contact your local agriculture office for up-to-date lists of varieties available.
        \n2. Maintain a clean field by removing the weeds and drying the rice field after plowing.
        \n3. Plant rice varieties of the same maturity date to break the insect’s cycle.
        \n4. Use of mercury bulbs as light traps for egg-laying adults, light trapping of insects should start 5 days before and after the full moon.
        \n5. Encourage biological control agents, such as small wasps (parasitize the eggs), ground beetles, spiders, crickets,
        and red ants (attack the eggs, nymphs, and adults), coccinellid beetles, ducks, toads (feed on eggs and nymphs), fungi species (attacks nymphs and adults).
        \n
        \nTo control black bug infestation:
        \n
        \n1. During early infestation, raise the water level in the field for 2−3 days to force the insects to move upwards.
        \n2. Flood the fields. This can cause higher egg mortality.
        \n3. After harvest, plow fields to remove remaining insects.
        \nSource:</string>
    <string name="rbb_hyperlink">
        <a href="http://www.knowledgebank.irri.org/training/fact-sheets/pest-management/insects/item/black-bug">
            knowledgebank.irri.org
        </a>
    </string>

    -------------------------------------------------<!--Rice Grain Bug-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="rgb_name">Rice Grain Bug</string>
    <string name="rgb_sci_name"> Paraeuscosmetus pallicomis</string>
    <string name="rgb_does">
        RGB damage rice by sucking out the contents of developing grains from pre-flowering spikelets
        to soft dough stage resulting [in] unfilled or empty grains and discoloration…Immature and adult rice grain bugs
        both feed on rice grains.
    </string>
    <string name="rgb_why_where">
        Female RGB [lay] their eggs singly; [these are] whitish or transparent in color…then
        [these turn] reddish to brown upon hatching.
        [A] newly emerged adult is light green to orange, while [a] fully developed adult [turns from] light brown to black
        in color and when disturbed or alarmed, hides among leaves, panicles, stubbles, and crevices…They can be seen walking
        or crawling, then [they] climb up and [go] down repeatedly from one rice [stubble] to another. It usually appears when
        the temperature becomes hotter, usually from 9 a.m. to 4 p.m., and [they can] be hardly found during [the] cool times
        of the day.
    </string>
    <string name="rgb_identify">

    </string>
    <string name="rgb_important">

    </string>
    <string name="rgb_pesticide">LAMDAXIN 2.5 EC \nAGRO CYPERMETHRIN 5 EC \nTRUGOLD 60 EC</string>
    <string name="rgb_active_ing">LAMBDA-CYHALOTHRIN 25 g/L \nN CYPERMETHRIN 50g/L \nDIAZINON 600 g/L</string>
    <string name="rgb_mngmnt">
        The land preparation is crucial in controlling the spread of the bug. RGB lays
        egg under the soil, and intensive plowing exposes their eggs to the sun, causing [these] to…[spoil, thus arresting]
        the insect’s growth. To preserve standing crops, especially those in the vegetative stage, farmers are advised to
        flood or soak the field for at least 10 hours to…spoil the eggs so [these cannot] hatch.
        \nSynchronous planting can help avoid [the] overlapping of [incidences] of insect population and disease occurrence.
        Harvesting at the same would enable farmers to observe the same fallow period (leaving the field idle for 30 days),
        which breaks [the] pest cycle and [destroys] its hosts.
    </string>
    <string name="rgb_hyperlink">
        Source:
        <a href=" source: https://www.agriculture.com.ph/2017/12/30/debugging-the-rice-grain-bug/">
            agriculture.com.ph
        </a>
    </string>

    -------------------------------------------------<!--Leaffolder-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="lf_name">Leaf Folder</string>
    <string name="lf_sci_name"> Cnaphalocrocis medinalis</string>
    <string name="lf_does">
        Leaffolder caterpillars fold a rice leaf around themselves and attach the leaf margins together with silk strands.
        \nThey feed inside the folded leaf creating longitudinal white and transparent streaks on the blade.
    </string>
    <string name="lf_why_where">
        Heavy use of fertilizer encourages rapid multiplication of the insect. High humidity and shady areas of the field,
        as well as the presence of grassy weeds from rice fields and surrounding borders favor the development of the pest.
        \n
        \nExpanded rice areas with irrigation systems, multiple rice cropping and insecticide induced resurgences are important factors in the insect’s abundance.
        \n
        \nRice leaffolders occur in all rice environments and are more abundant during the rainy seasons.
        They are commonly found in shady areas and areas where rice is heavily fertilized. In tropical rice areas,
        they are active year-round, whereas in temperate countries they are active from May to October.
        The adults are nocturnal and during the day, they stay under shade to escape predation. Moths fly short distances when disturbed.
    </string>
    <string name="lf_identify">
        Check the plant for the following symptoms:
        \n
        \n-longitudinal and transparent whitish streaks on damaged leaves
        \n-tubular folded leaves
        \n-leaf tips sometimes fastened to the basal part of leaf
        \n-heavily infested fields appear scorched with many folded leaves
        \n
        \nAlso check for presence of insects, particularly during tillering to flowering. Signs include:
        \n
        \n-disc-shaped ovoid eggs laid singly,
        \n-young larvae feeding on the base of the youngest unopened leaves,
        \n-folded leaves enclosing the feeding larvae, and
        \n-present fecal matter.
    </string>
    <string name="lf_important">
        The damage caused by leaffolders may be important when it affects more than half of the flag leaf and the next two youngest leaves in each tiller.
        \n
        \nAt vegetative phase, crops can generally recover from damage; but when leaffolders infest at reproductive phase,
        the damage can be economically important. High feeding damage on the flag leaves can cause yield loss.
        \n
        \nMost early season insecticide use have little or no economic returns. Instead,
        it can cause ecological disruptions in natural biological control processes, thus enhancing the development of secondary pests, such as planthoppers.
    </string>
    <string name="lf_pesticide">TREBON 10 EC \nSUNO CYPERMETHRIN 5 EC \nTRUGOLD 60 EC</string>
    <string name="lf_active_ing">ETOFENPROX 25g/L \nCYPERMETHRIN 55 g/L n\DIAZINON 600g/L</string>
    <string name="lf_mngmnt">
        To prevent leaf folder outbreaks:
        \n• Use resistant varieties.
        \n• Contact your local agriculture office for an up-to-date list of available varieties.
        \n• Follow rice with a different crop, or fallow period.
        \n• Avoid ratooning.
        \n• Flood and plow field after harvesting if possible.
        \n• Remove grassy weeds from fields and borders.
        \n• Reduce density of planting.
        \n• Use balanced fertilizer rates.
        \n• Spraying pesticides is not advisable during early crop stages.
        \nMany farmers in Asia lack the necessary safety equipment and expertise
        to use pesticides safely and therefore should not use them. See a crop
        protection specialist for guidance specific to your situation.
    </string>
    <string name="lf_hyperlink">
        Source:
        <a href="http://www.knowledgebank.irri.org/training/fact-sheets/pest-management/insects/item/rice-leaffolder">
            knowledgebank.irri.org.
        </a>
    </string>
</resources>