<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
     <string name="source_link">
         Knowledge Bank: <a href="http://www.knowledgebank.irri.org/step-by-step-production/growth/pests-and-diseases/insects">www.knowledgebank.irri.org.</a>
    </string>
    -------------------------------------------------<!--Brown Planthopper-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="bph_name">Brown Planthopper</string>
    <string name="bph_sci_name">Nilaparvata lugens</string>
    <string name="bph_does">
        High population of planthoppers cause leaves to initially turn orange-yellow before becoming brown and dry and this is a
        condition called hopperburn that kills the plant.
        \n
        \nBPH can also transmit Rice Ragged Stunt and Rice Grassy Stunt diseases. Neither disease can be cured.
    </string>
    <string name="bph_why_where">
       Planthoppers can be a problem in rainfed and in irrigated wetland environments.
        It also occurs in areas with continuous submerged
        conditions in the field, high shade, and humidity.
        \n
        \nClosed canopy of the rice plants, densely seeded crops, excessive use of nitrogen,
        and early season insecticide spraying also favors insect development.
    </string>
    <string name="bph_identify"><![CDATA[
        Check for the presence of insect:
        \n
        \n-crescent-shaped white eggs inserted into the midrib or leaf sheath
        \n-white to brown nymphs
        \n-brown or white adults feeding near the base of tillers
        \n
        \nCheck the field for:
        \n
        \n-hopperburn or yellowing, browning and drying of plant
        \n-ovipositional marks exposing the plant to fungal and bacterial infections
        \n-presence of honeydew and sooty molds in the bases of areas infected
        \n-plants with ragged stunt or grassy stunt virus disease
        \n
        \nHopperburn is similar to the feeding damage or "bugburn" caused by the rice black bug.
        To confirm hopperburn caused by planthoppers,
        check for the presence of sooty molds at the base of the plant.
    ]]></string>
    <string name="bph_pesticide">
        ACE ASSAULT 50 SC
        \nACE CARTAP 50 SP
        \nAGCHEM FIPRONIL 5 SC
        \nTORPEDO 5 EC
        \nKNOCK OUT 5 EC
    </string>
    <string name="bph_active_ing">
        PHENTHOATE
      \nPHENTHOATE+BPMC
       \nCYPERMETHRIN
    </string>

    <string name="bph_important">
        The feeding damage caused by planthoppers results in the yellowing of the plants. At high population density,
        hopperburn or complete drying of the plants is observed. At this level, crop loss may be 100%.
        In field conditions, plants nearing maturity can have hopperburns if infested with about 400−500 BPH nymphs.
    </string>
    <string name="bph_mngmnt"><![CDATA[
        Outbreaks result from pesticides destroying natural enemies (BPH eggs hatch unchecked, and surviving
        BPH quickly build-up populations to
            damaging levels), or when longwinged planthoppers are being carried in by the wind.
        \n
        \nTo prevent outbreaks of planthopper:
        \n
        \n1. Remove weeds from the field and surrounding areas.
        \n2. Avoid indiscriminate use of insecticide, which destroys natural enemies.
        \n3. Use a resistant variety. Contact your local agriculture office for an up-to-date list of available varieties.
        \n4. Critical numbers: At a density of 1 BPH/stem or less there is still time to act in case the numbers increase.
        \n5. Look for BPH daily in the seedbed, or weekly in the field, on stems and the water surface. Check each side of
            the seed bed (or direct-seeded fields). For older rice plants, grasp the plant, bend it over slightly, and gently
            tap it near the base to see if planthoppers fall onto the water surface. For transplanted rice look at bases of 10
            to 20 hills as you cross the field diagonally. There is no need to scout for BPH or WBPH beyond the milk stage.
        \n6. Use light traps (e.g., an electric bulb or kerosene lamp near a light colored wall or over a pan of water) at night
            when rice is prone to planthopper attack. Do not place lights near seedbeds or fields. If the light trap is inundated
            with hundreds of BPH, it\'s a signal to check your seedbed or field immediately; then scout every day for the next
            few weeks. If farmers monitor on a daily basis anyway, then a light trap is unnecessary.
        \n
        \nTo control planthoppers:
        \n
        \nMechanical & physical measures
        \n
        \n-Flood the seedbed, for a day, so that only the tips of seedlings are exposed will control BPH.
        \n-Sweep small seedbeds with a net to remove some BPH (but not eggs), particularly from dry seed beds. At high BPH densities,
            sweeping will not remove sufficient numbers of BPH from the base of the plant.
        \n
        \nBiological control
        \n
        \n-If natural enemies out-number BPH the risk of hopperburn is low. Even rice already damaged by hopperburn should
            not be treated with insecticides if natural enemies out-number BPH. Natural enemies of BPH include water striders,
            mirid bugs, spiders, and various egg parasitoids.
        \n
        \nChemical control
        \n
        \nOnly apply insecticides to the seedbed, for BPH or WBPH, if all of these conditions are met:
        \n
        \n-an average of more than one planthopper per stem,
        \n-on average, more planthoppers than natural enemies,
        \n-flooding the seedbed is not an option.
    ]]></string>
<!--<string name="bph_hyperlink">
        Source:
        <a href="http://www.knowledgebank.irri.org/training/fact-sheets/pest-management/insects/item/planthopper">
            knowledgebank.irri.org
        </a>
    </string>-->
-------------------------------------------------<!--Green Leaf Hopper-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="glh_name">Green Planthopper</string>
    <string name="glh_sci_name">Nephotettix virescens</string>
    <string name="glh_does">
       Green leafhoppers are the most common leafhoppers in rice fields and are primarily critical because they spread
        the viral disease tungro. Both nymphs and adults feed by extracting plant sap with their needle-shaped mouthparts.
    </string>
    <string name="glh_why_where">
        Staggered planting encourages population growth of GLH.
        \n
        \nGreen leafhoppers are common in rainfed and irrigated wetland environments. They are not prevalent in upland rice.
            Both the nymphs and adults feed on the dorsal surface of the leaf blades rather than the ventral surface.
        They prefer to feed on the lateral leaves rather than the leaf sheaths and the middle leaves.
        They also prefer rice plants that have been fertilized with large amount of nitrogen.
    </string>
    <string name="glh_important">
        Green leafhoppers are important pests. They are vectors of viral diseases such as tungro, yellow dwarf,
        yellow-orange leaf, transitory yellowing, and dwarf.
    </string>
    <string name="glh_identify">
        Rice fields infested by GLH can have tungro, yellow dwarf, yellow-orange leaf, and transitory yellowing diseases.
        \n
        \nSymptoms include:
        \n
        \n-stunted plants and reduced vigor
        \nreduced number of productive tillers
        \n-withering or complete plant drying
        \n
        \nTungro infected crops may sometimes be confused with nitrogen deficiency or iron toxicity or acid soils.
        To confirm the cause of the problem, check for virus infected plants in the fields, and the presence of the insect:
        \n
        \n-white or pale yellow eggs inside leaf sheaths or midribs
        \nyellow or pale green nymphs with or without black markings
        \npale green adults with or without black markings feeding on upper parts of the crop
    </string>
    <string name="glh_pesticide">
        ACE CARTAP 50 SP
        \nPERMECHEM 10 EC
        \nPHENTO‐M 50 EC
        \nCARDAN 50 SP
        \nSTRENGTH 40 SP
    </string>
    <string name="glh_active_ing">
       LAMBDA‐CYHALOTHRIN
        \nCYPERMETHRIN
        \nPHENTHOATE
    </string>

    <string name="glh_mngmnt"><![CDATA[
        1. Use GLH-resistant and tungro-resistant varieties. Contact your local agriculture office for an up-to-date
            list of available varieties.
        \n2. Reduce the number of rice crops to two per year and synchronized crop establishment across farms reduces
        leafhoppers and other insect vectors.
        \n3. Transplant older seedlings (>3 weeks) to reduce viral disease susceptibility transmitted by leafhoppers.
        \n4. Plant early within a given planting period, particularly in the dry season to reduce the risk of insect-vector disease.
        \n5. Avoid planting during the peak of GLH activity (shown by historical records) to avoid infestation. Light traps can be
        used to show GLH numbers.
        \n6. Apply nitrogen as needed (e.g., using the Leaf Color Chart) to avoid contributing to population outbreaks by applying
        too much nitrogen, or hindering
            plant recovery from planthopper damage by applying insufficient nitrogen.
        \n7. Control weeds in the field and on the bunds to remove the preferred grassy hosts of GLH and promotes crop vigor.
        \n8. Perform crop rotation with a non-rice crop during the dry season to decrease alternate hosts for diseases.
        \n9. Intercrop upland rice with soybean to reduce the incidence of leafhoppers on rice.
        \n
        \nIn areas without tungro source, insecticides are not needed, avoid spraying of insecticide (it is often unable
        to prevent or reduce tungro infections).
        \n
        \nEncourage biological control agents: small wasps (parasitize the eggs), mirid bug; strepsipterans, small wasps,
        pipunculid flies, and nematodes (parasitize both the nymphs and adults), aquatic veliid bugs, nabid bugs, empid
        flies, damselflies, dragonflies, and spiders, fungal pathogen (attacks both nymph and adult).
    ]]></string>
<!-- <string name="glh_hyperlink">
        Source:
        <a href="http://www.knowledgebank.irri.org/training/fact-sheets/pest-management/insects">
                    knowledgebank.irri.org
        </a>
    </string>-->
 -------------------------------------------------<!--Rice Bug-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="rb_name">Rice Bug</string>
    <string name="rb_sci_name">Leptocorisa acuta</string>
    <string name="rb_does">
            Rice bugs damage rice by sucking out the contents of developing grains from pre-flowering spikelets to soft dough stage,
        therefore causing unfilled or empty grains and discoloration. Immature and adult rice bugs both feed on rice grains.
    </string>
    <string name="rb_why_where">
        - They are caused by factors such as nearby woodlands, extensive weedy areas near rice fields, wild grasses near canals,
        and staggered rice planting.
        \n- The insect also turns active when the monsoonal rains start.
        \n- At the end of the rainy season, the rice bug population grows.
    </string>
    <string name="rb_identify"><![CDATA[
        Check the plant for feeding damage, such as
        \n- uneven or spotted grains;
        \n- empty grains; and
        \n- erect panicles.
        \n
        \nThe symptoms can be mistaken for damage brought on by nutritional shortages or flower thrips. To confirm rice bug
        infestation, check for presence of insect:
        \n- Along the leaf\'s midrib are a row of round, glossy, reddish-brown eggs.
        \n- Slender, brownish-green nymphs and adults consuming rice grains&apos; endosperm
        \n- Unpleasant smell
    ]]></string>
    <string name="rb_important">
        Both the adults and nymphs feed on grains at the milking stage. They can be serious pests of rice and
        sometimes reduce yield by as much as 30%.
    </string>
    <string name="rb_pesticide">
        AGCHEM FIPRONIL 5 SC
        \nRPG 2.5 EC
        \nBANKER 2.5 EC
        \nAGROTECHNO ZAP 50 SC
        \nBIDA 2.5 EC
    </string>
    <string name="rb_active_ing">LAMBDA-CYHALOTHRIN 25 g/L \nDIAZINON 600 g/L \nN CYPERMETHRIn 50g/L</string>
    <string name="rb_mngmnt"><![CDATA[
      - Remove weeds from nearby areas and fields during dry seasons.
      \n- Synchronous planting, which involves planting all of the fields in a village at once, also lessens the
        issues caused by rice pests.
      \n- Capturing rice bugs by net in the early morning or late afternoon.
       \n
        \nFor chemical control
      \nContact a crop protection specialist before applying a pesticide for guidance, direction, and cautions tailored to
        your situation.
      \n- Start field scouting at pre-flowering and keep going every day until the hard dough stage. Walk diagonally across a
        transplanted field and count rice bugs in the early morning or late afternoon from 20 hills. If there are more than
        10 rice bugs/20 hills, immediate action may be needed.
      \n- Numerous variables, including the application equipment available, insecticide price, applicator experience,
        and fish presence, influence the choice of insecticide. It is necessary to balance the advantages of applying
        an insecticide against the environmental and health risks.
]]></string>
<!-- <string name="rb_hyperlink">
        Source:
        <a href="http://www.knowledgebank.irri.org/training/fact-sheets/pest-management/insects/item/rice-bug">
            knowledgebank.irri.org
        </a>
    </string>-->
    -------------------------------------------------<!--Rice Black Bug-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="rbb_name">Rice Black Bug</string>
    <string name="rbb_sci_name">Scotinophara coarctata</string>
    <string name="rbb_does">
        Black bugs remove the sap of the plant. They can cause browning of leaves, deadheart, and bugburn.
        Their damage also causes stunting in plants, reduced tiller number, and formation of whiteheads.
        \n
        \nOn severe cases, black bugs weaken the plant preventing them from producing seeds.
    </string>
    <string name="rbb_why_where">
        - Rainfed and irrigated wetland.
        \n- Farms with poor drainage and continually farmed irrigated rice lands.
        \n- Damages are most frequently seen in dry season rice crops and densely planted fields.

    </string>
    <string name="rbb_identify"><![CDATA[
        1. Check leaves for discoloration. Black bug damage can cause reddish brown or yellowing of plants. Leaves also have
        chlorotic lesions.
      \n2. Check for decreased tillering. Bugburn symptoms show wilting of tillers with no visible honeydew deposits or sooty molds.
      \n3. Plants are also stunted; and can develop stunted panicles, no panicles, incompletely exerted panicles, and unfilled
        spikelets
        or whiteheads at booting stage.
      \n4. Check for deadhearts.
      \n
      \n Deadhearts can also be caused by stemborer. To confirm cause of damage, pull infected plants. In black bug damage,
        infected plants cannot be pulled at the bases.
      \n
      \n Heavy infestation and "bugburn" is usually visible after heading or maturing.
    ]]></string>
    <string name="rbb_important">
        Black bug feeds on the rice plant from seedling to maturity growth stages. Ten black bug adults per hill can cause
        losses of up to 35% in some rice.
    </string>
    <string name="rbb_pesticide">
        ZULPAC LAMBDA 2.5 EC
        \nFLARE 2.5 EC
        \nSTILLETO 25 EC
        \nBANKER 2.5 EC
        \nLABRYS 2.5 EC
    </string>
    <string name="rbb_active_ing">
        DELTAMETHRIN 25 g/L
        \nBETA-CYPERMETHRIN 25 g/L
        \nAZADIRACHTIN 3g/L
    </string>
    <string name="rbb_mngmnt"><![CDATA[
        Integrated Management of Rice Black Bug
        \n
        \nTo prevent black bug infestation:
        \n1. Use resistant varieties.
        \n   1.1 Contact your local agriculture office for up-to-date lists of varieties available.
        \n2. Maintain a clean field by removing the weeds and drying the rice field after plowing.
        \n3. Plant rice varieties of the same maturity date to break the insect\'s cycle.
        \n4. Use of mercury bulbs as light traps for egg-laying adults, light trapping of insects should start
        5 days before and after the full moon.
        \n5. Encourage biological control agents, such as small wasps (parasitize the eggs), ground beetles, spiders, crickets,
        and red ants (attack the eggs, nymphs, and adults), coccinellid beetles, ducks, toads (feed on eggs and nymphs),
        fungi species (attacks nymphs and adults).
        \n
        \nTo control black bug infestation:
        \n
        \n1. During early infestation, raise the water level in the field for 2−3 days to force the insects to move upwards.
        \n2. Flood the fields. This can cause higher egg mortality.
        \n3. After harvest, plow fields to remove remaining insects.
        ]]></string>
<!--<string name="rbb_hyperlink">
        <a href="http://www.knowledgebank.irri.org/training/fact-sheets/pest-management/insects/item/black-bug">
            knowledgebank.irri.org
        </a>
    </string>-->
    -------------------------------------------------<!--Rice Grain Bug-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="rgb_name">Rice Grain Bug</string>
    <string name="rgb_sci_name"> Paraeuscosmetus pallicomis</string>
    <string name="rgb_does">
        The rice grain bug is responsible for the discoloration of the leaves and grains, which is considered
        to be a sign of nutrient deficiency.
    </string>
    <string name="rgb_why_where">
        RGBs are more prevalent in highland and rainfed rice. Its high population is influenced by a variety of causes,
        including extensive weedy regions close to rice fields, wild grasses close to canals, and staggered rice planting.
    </string>
    <string name="rgb_identify"><![CDATA[
        - RGBs are tiny, swiftly moving insects that resemble ants and are roughly the size of a rice grain from thorax
        to abdomen, measuring between 0.6 to 0.9 cm.
        \n- A fully mature adult\'s color changes from light green to orange, while an adult that has just emerged changes
        from light brown to black. They can be seen walking or crawling a s they continually go up and down from one rice stubble
        to another.  It typically starts to appear around 9 a.m. when the weather gets warm. to 4 p.m., and they are virtually
        ever seen during the cooler hours.
        \n- Additionally, it possesses a piercing-sucking mouth section that is utilized to pierce the seed covering and access
        the nutrient-rich interior.

    ]]></string>
    <string name="rgb_important">

    </string>
    <string name="rgb_pesticide">
        ORTHENE 75 SP
        \nTERMINATOR 2.5 EC
        \nAGCHEM FIPRONIL 5 SC
        \nLABRYS 2.5 EC
        \nASCEND 50 SC
    </string>
    <string name="rgb_active_ing">
        LAMBDA-CYHALOTHRIN 25 g/L
        \nN CYPERMETHRIN 50g/L
        \nDIAZINON 600 g/L</string>
    <string name="rgb_mngmnt">
       It is important to practice synchronous planting, in which rice develops and expands at the same rate throughout a
        region, as this reduces the likelihood of insect damage spreading.
    </string>
    <!--<string name="rgb_hyperlink">
        Source:
        <a href=" source: https://www.agriculture.com.ph/2017/12/30/debugging-the-rice-grain-bug/">
            agriculture.com.ph
        </a>
    </string>-->

    -------------------------------------------------<!--Leaffolder-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="lf_name">Leaf Folder</string>
    <string name="lf_sci_name"> Cnaphalocrocis medinalis</string>
    <string name="lf_does">
        Leaffolder caterpillars fold a rice leaf around themselves and attach the leaf margins together with silk strands.
        \nThey feed inside the folded leaf creating longitudinal white and transparent streaks on the blade.
    </string>
    <string name="lf_why_where"><![CDATA[
        Expanded rice areas with irrigation systems, multiple rice cropping and insecticide induced resurgences are important
        factors in the insect\'s abundance.
        \nRice leaffolders occur in all rice environments and are more abundant during the rainy seasons. In tropical rice
        areas, they are active year-round, whereas in temperate countries they are active from May to October. The adults
        are nocturnal and during the day, they stay under shade to escape predation where rice is heavily fertilized. Moths
        fly short distances when disturbed.

    ]]></string>
    <string name="lf_identify">
        Check the plant for the following symptoms:
        \n
        \n-longitudinal and transparent whitish streaks on damaged leaves
        \n-tubular folded leaves
        \n-leaf tips sometimes fastened to the basal part of leaf
        \n-heavily infested fields appear scorched with many folded leaves
        \n
        \nAlso check for presence of insects, particularly during tillering to flowering. Signs include:
        \n
        \n-disc-shaped ovoid eggs laid singly,
        \n-young larvae feeding on the base of the youngest unopened leaves,
        \n-folded leaves enclosing the feeding larvae, and
        \n-present fecal matter.
    </string>
    <string name="lf_important">
    The damage caused by leaffolders may be important when it affects more than half of the flag leaf and the next
        two youngest leaves in each tiller. High feeding damage on the flag leaves can cause yield loss.
    </string>
    <string name="lf_pesticide">
        ACE ASSAULT 50 SC
        \nAGRISOLUTIONS POLARIS LAMBDA 2.5 EC
        \nSUPRA 5 EC
        \nSUMO 2.5 EC
        \nAGCHEM FIPRONIL 5 SC
    </string>
    <string name="lf_active_ing">
        ETOFENPROX 25g/L
        \nCYPERMETHRIN 55 g/L
        \nDIAZINON 600g/L</string>
    <string name="lf_mngmnt">
        To prevent leaf folder outbreaks:
        \n- Use resistant varieties.
        \n- Contact your local agriculture office for an up-to-date list of available varieties.
        \n- Follow rice with a different crop, or fallow period.
        \n- Avoid ratooning.
        \n- Flood and plow field after harvesting if possible.
        \n- Remove grassy weeds from fields and borders.
        \n- Reduce density of planting.
        \n- Use balanced fertilizer rates.
        \n- Spraying pesticides is not advisable during early crop stages.
        \nMany farmers in Asia lack the necessary safety equipment and expertise
        to use pesticides safely and therefore should not use them. See a crop
        protection specialist for guidance specific to your situation.
    </string>
    <!-- <string name="lf_hyperlink">
        Source:
        <a href="http://www.knowledgebank.irri.org/training/fact-sheets/pest-management/insects/item/rice-leaffolder">
            knowledgebank.irri.org.
        </a>
    </string>-->
</resources>