<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    -------------------------------------------------<!--Brown Planthopper-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="bph_name">Brown Planthopper</string>
    <string name="bph_sci">Nilaparvata lugens</string>
    <string name="bph_lifeCycle">
        • Eggs are laid in batches inside the leaf sheaths and on the leaf midribs.
      \n• Nymphs are brown.
      \n• Nymphs molt 5 times within 13-15 days before becoming adults.
      \n• It takes 7-9 days for the eggs to hatch into nymphs.
    </string>
    <string name="bph_dmg">
        • Adults and nymphs feed at the base of the tillers and remove the plant sap.
      \n• Plants turn yellow and dry rapidly.
      \n• Heavy infestations are characterized by patches of dried plants in circular manner. This condition is referred to as hopper burn.
      \n• Honeydew excreted on infested plants becomes a medium for growth of sooty mold fungus, which interferes with normal plant functions BPH transmit
      \nSource:
      \nhttps://www.agriculture.com.ph/2019/12/16/management-of-planthoppers-and-leafhoppers/
    </string>
    <string name="bph_pesticide">
        PHENOM 50 EC \nPHENDEX 350 EC \nDISCOVERY 5 EC
    </string>
    <string name="bph_activeI">
        PHENTHOATE
      \nPHENTHOATE+BPMC
       \nCYPERMETHRIN
    </string>

    <string name="bph_mngmnt">
        \nOveruse of insecticides is the main cause of outbreaks of brown planthopper.
        When insecticides are used, predators and parasites are killed, and brown planthopper populations
        \'resurge\', i.e., the numbers after spraying are higher than before; this is because there are no natural enemies.
        Integrated Pest Management - IPM - programs stress the need to maintain biological control of natural enemies, and also include tolerant varieties.
        The routine use of broad-spectrum insecticides should always be avoided.
        \nNATURAL ENEMIES
        \nThere are a number of natural predators of the brown planthopper: spiders eat the nymphs and adults, as do coccinellid beetles (ladybird beetles),
        dragonflies, damselflies, and mirid egg-sucking bugs. There are two species of egg-sucking bugs in the Pacific islands - Cyrtorhinus chinensis and
        Cyrtorhinus lividipennis - and there are likely to be wasp parasitoids that attack eggs, as well as fungal pathogens and mites.
        \nCULTURAL CONTROL
        \nBefore planting:
        \n•Choose varieties that have tolerance to the brown plant hopper.
        \n•Avoid staggered planting, preventing planthoppers moving from older to younger crops in ever greater numbers. Plant at the same time as neighbours, within a period of 2-3 weeks.
        \n•Remove volunteer plants.
        \n•Rotate rice with other crops. Do not plant rice crops one after another so that large populations of the brown planthopper can migrate easily between them.
        \nDuring growth:
        \n•Drain the paddies for 3-4 days during the early stage of infestation.
        \n•Apply split applications (three times) of nitrogen fertilizer, not all at one time.
        \n•Allow plants (weeds) on the bunds (and at the borders of dryland crops), and between fields, to flower in order to attract natural enemies.
        \n•After harvest:
        \n•Do not ratoon the crop, i.e., do not allow it to resprout and continue growing after harvest.
        \n•Plough the field after harvest, removing the stubble that would otherwise allow the brown planthoppers to continue to breed.
  RESISTANT VARIETIES
Many varieties have been bred for resistance to brown planthoppers; unfortunately, there are many instances where changes occur in the planthoppers allowing them to overcome the resistance. </string>

-------------------------------------------------<!--Green Leaf Hopper-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="glf_name">Green Leaffolder</string>
    <string name="glf_sci">Nephotettix nigropictus</string>
    <string name="glf_lifeCycle">
        • Eggs are laid in small slits made in the soft parts of the leaf sheaths.
      \n• Newly laid eggs are barely visible and are cylindrical, banana-shaped, and pale yellow.
      \n• Nymphs emerge from eggs in 6-8 days.
      \n• Nymphs have varied color pattern on the noctum (neck).
      \n• The first instar nymphs are numerous on the lower surface of older leaf blades, but from second instar onwards,
            they distribute themselves evenly on the leaves.
      \n• There are five instars before they become adult.
      \n• The total life cycle from egg to adult is 22-26 days.
    </string>
    <string name="glf_dmg">
        • Adults and nymphs rarely cause serious feeding damage to rice plant, unlike planthoppers.
      \n• GLF transmit viruses (tungro and dwarf) and mycoplasma agents of yellow dwarf and orange leaf diseases.
      \nSource:
      \nhttps://www.agriculture.com.ph/2019/12/16/management-of-planthoppers-and-leafhoppers/
    </string>
    <string name="glf_pesticide">
        LAMDAXIN 2.5 EC \nAGRO CYPERMETHRIN 5 EC \nPHENOM 50 EC
    </string>
    <string name="glf_activeI">
       LAMBDA‐CYHALOTHRIN \nCYPERMETHRIN  \nPHENTHOATE
    </string>

 -------------------------------------------------<!--Rice Bug-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="rb_name">Rice Bug</string>
    <string name="rb_sci">Leptocorisa acuta</string>
    <string name="rb_lifeCycle">Young nymphs are green while adults are greenish‐brown. When the
                                \ntemperature is high, and the insects are not feeding, they
                                \ncamouflage themselves on the plant by taking up a particular
                                \nposture.
                                \nAdults longevity is 30‐50 days, although reports of 110‐115 days
                                \nwhen reared individually. Mating starts 7‐14 days after becoming
                                \nadult. Pre‐oviposition period is within 3‐4 days. Eggs hatch in 5‐8
                                \ndays
                                \nA female lays 200‐300 eggs in batches of 10‐20 eggs. Females rest
                                \non grassy areas and the base of the plant during sunlight.
                                \nhttps://www.pinoyrice.com/wp-content/uploads/rice-bug.pdf</string>
    <string name="rb_pesticide">LAMDAXIN 2.5 EC \nTRUGOLD 60 EC \nSUPERSMAK 50 EC</string>
    <string name="rb_activeI">LAMBDA-CYHALOTHRIN 25 g/L \nDIAZINON 600 g/L \nN CYPERMETHRIn 50g/L</string>
    <string name="rb_mngmnt">Cultural
                            \n• Eliminate grassy weeds from rice fields, levees, and surrounding areas by either cutting or
                            burning to reduce habitats for egg‐laying.
                            \n• Avoid staggered planting of fields in the area to break continuous food source.
                            \n• Smoking the field by burning straw windward, and passing baskets or bags coated on the inside
                            with sticky material are promising in repelling/capturing them.
                            \n• Netting and handpicking bugs reduce their numbers.
                            \n• Put attractants such as arasan or anything with bad odor like dead snails or rats. The bugs that
                            are gathered around the attractants can be burned or sprayed with chemicals to reduce their
                            numbers.
                            \n• Awned varieties are resistant
                            \n• Varieties with panicles enclosed in the leaf sheath for longer time offer some mechanical
                            resistance to feeding.
                            \n
                            \nBiological
                            \n• Small wasps and long‐horned grasshoppers kill eggs.
                            \n• Fungal pathogens infect nymphs and adults.
                            \n•Spiders, crickets, lady beetles, and long‐horned grasshoppers feed on nymphs and adults.  </string>

    -------------------------------------------------<!--Rice Black Bug-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="rbb_name">Rice Black Bug</string>
    <string name="rbb_sci">Oryza sativa</string>
    <string name="rbb_lifeCycle"> </string>
    <string name="rbb_pesticide">NIMBECIDINE \nCHIX 2.5 EC \nDECIS 2.5 EC</string>
    <string name="rbb_activeI">DELTAMETHRIN 25 g/L \nBETA-CYPERMETHRIN 25 g/L \nAZADIRACHTIN 3g/L</string>
    <string name="rbb_mngmnt">Integrated Management of Rice Black Bug
        1. Grow Rice Black Bug (RBB)‐tolerant varieties.
        \nUse tolerant varieties such as IR 1314, IR 44526, and
        IR 10871‐75‐3‐2‐2 to minimize yield loss from RBB
        attacks.  Grow these only in areas where tungro is
        not a problem because these varieties are highly
        susceptible to tungro.
        \n2. Plant early‐maturing varieties during the regular planting time in the community.
        \nSynchronous planting must be made over large contiguous areas, preferably over a 1 km radius within a
        locality. This is to evade the damaging population levels of RBB and to break its life cycle.
        \n3. Conserve and augment natural enemies of RBB.
        \nConserve natural enemies of RBB by not using chemicals that will kill them. Augment natural enemies of RBB
        by introducing parasitoids and pathogens in areas where they are not present.
        \n4. Weed control (sanitation).
        \nControl weeds to remove alternate hosts that serve as breeding sites for RBB.
        \n5. Use trap crop.
        \nEssentially, a trap crop is a small planting of a crop that is more attractive to RBB than the crop to be
        protected. Use this to divert colonizing individuals of RBB to a trap crop where they can be destroyed.
        \n6. Plow immediately after harvest.
        \nAll stages of RBB are present on rice stubbles, thus incorporating the stubbles into the soil destroys their
        breeding/hiding habitat.
        \n7. Flood the field.
        \nTo determine whether RBB eggs are parasitized or not, collect about 5 egg masses and place them inside a
        container. Cover the mouth of the container with a nylon mesh and wait for about a week for parasitoids
        (wasps) to emerge. If no wasps emerge, flood the area.
        \n8. Release ducks in rice fields.
        \nDucks eat RBB and other pests so release them in an
        insecticide‐free rice fields with standing water about a month
        after transplanting up to heading.
        \n9. Apply metarhizium anisopliae
        \nhttps://www.pinoyrice.com/wp-content/uploads/rice-black-bug.pdf</string>

    -------------------------------------------------<!--Rice Grain Bug-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="rgb_name">Rice Grain Bug</string>
    <string name="rgb_sci"> Paraeuscosmetus pallicomis</string>
    <string name="rgb_lifeCycle">T</string>
    <string name="rgb_pesticide">LAMDAXIN 2.5 EC \nAGRO CYPERMETHRIN 5 EC \nTRUGOLD 60 EC</string>
    <string name="rgb_activeI">LAMBDA-CYHALOTHRIN 25 g/L \nN CYPERMETHRIN 50g/L \nDIAZINON 600 g/L</string>

    -------------------------------------------------<!--Leaffolder-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="lf_name">Leaffolder</string>
    <string name="lf_sci"> </string>
    <string name="lf_pesticide">TREBON 10 EC \nSUNO CYPERMETHRIN 5 EC \nTRUGOLD 60 EC</string>
    <string name="lf_activeI">ETOFENPROX 25g/L \nCYPERMETHRIN 55 g/L n\DIAZINON 600g/L</string>

</resources>