<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    -------------------------------------------------<!--Brown Planthopper-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="bph_name">Brown Planthopper</string>
    <string name="bph_sci">Nilaparvata lugens</string>
    <string name="bph_lifeCycle">
        • Eggs are laid in batches inside the leaf sheaths and on the leaf midribs.
      \n• Nymphs are brown.
      \n• Nymphs molt 5 times within 13-15 days before becoming adults.
      \n• It takes 7-9 days for the eggs to hatch into nymphs.
    </string>
    <string name="bph_dmg">
        • Adults and nymphs feed at the base of the tillers and remove the plant sap.
      \n• Plants turn yellow and dry rapidly.
      \n• Heavy infestations are characterized by patches of dried plants in circular manner. This condition is referred to as hopper burn.
      \n• Honeydew excreted on infested plants becomes a medium for growth of sooty mold fungus, which interferes with normal plant functions BPH transmit
      \nSource:
        <!--https://www.agriculture.com.ph/2019/12/16/management-of-planthoppers-and-leafhoppers/-->
    </string>
    <string name="bph_pesticide">
        PHENOM 50 EC \nPHENDEX 350 EC \nDISCOVERY 5 EC
    </string>
    <string name="bph_activeI">
        PHENTHOATE
      \nPHENTHOATE+BPMC
       \nCYPERMETHRIN
    </string>

    <string name="bph_mngmnt">
        \nOveruse of insecticides is the main cause of outbreaks of brown planthopper.
        When insecticides are used, predators and parasites are killed, and brown planthopper populations
        \'resurge\', i.e., the numbers after spraying are higher than before; this is because there are no natural enemies.
        Integrated Pest Management - IPM - programs stress the need to maintain biological control of natural enemies, and also include tolerant varieties.
        The routine use of broad-spectrum insecticides should always be avoided.
        \nNATURAL ENEMIES
        \nThere are a number of natural predators of the brown planthopper: spiders eat the nymphs and adults, as do coccinellid beetles (ladybird beetles),
        dragonflies, damselflies, and mirid egg-sucking bugs. There are two species of egg-sucking bugs in the Pacific islands - Cyrtorhinus chinensis and
        Cyrtorhinus lividipennis - and there are likely to be wasp parasitoids that attack eggs, as well as fungal pathogens and mites.
        \nCULTURAL CONTROL
        \nBefore planting:
        \n•Choose varieties that have tolerance to the brown plant hopper.
        \n•Avoid staggered planting, preventing planthoppers moving from older to younger crops in ever greater numbers. Plant at the same time as neighbours, within a period of 2-3 weeks.
        \n•Remove volunteer plants.
        \n•Rotate rice with other crops. Do not plant rice crops one after another so that large populations of the brown planthopper can migrate easily between them.
        \nDuring growth:
        \n•Drain the paddies for 3-4 days during the early stage of infestation.
        \n•Apply split applications (three times) of nitrogen fertilizer, not all at one time.
        \n•Allow plants (weeds) on the bunds (and at the borders of dryland crops), and between fields, to flower in order to attract natural enemies.
        \n•After harvest:
        \n•Do not ratoon the crop, i.e., do not allow it to resprout and continue growing after harvest.
        \n•Plough the field after harvest, removing the stubble that would otherwise allow the brown planthoppers to continue to breed.
        \nRESISTANT VARIETIES
        \nMany varieties have been bred for resistance to brown planthoppers; unfortunately, there are many instances where changes occur in the planthoppers allowing them to overcome the resistance. </string>
        <!--https://apps.lucidcentral.org/pppw_v10/text/web_full/entities/rice_brown_planthopper_064.htm-->
-------------------------------------------------<!--Green Leaf Hopper-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="glf_name">Green Leaffolder</string>
    <string name="glf_sci">Nephotettix nigropictus</string>
    <string name="glf_lifeCycle">
        • Eggs are laid in small slits made in the soft parts of the leaf sheaths.
      \n• Newly laid eggs are barely visible and are cylindrical, banana-shaped, and pale yellow.
      \n• Nymphs emerge from eggs in 6-8 days.
      \n• Nymphs have varied color pattern on the noctum (neck).
      \n• The first instar nymphs are numerous on the lower surface of older leaf blades, but from second instar onwards,
            they distribute themselves evenly on the leaves.
      \n• There are five instars before they become adult.
      \n• The total life cycle from egg to adult is 22-26 days.
    </string>
    <string name="glf_dmg">
        • Adults and nymphs rarely cause serious feeding damage to rice plant, unlike planthoppers.
      \n• GLF transmit viruses (tungro and dwarf) and mycoplasma agents of yellow dwarf and orange leaf diseases.
      \nSource:
    <!--https://www.agriculture.com.ph/2019/12/16/management-of-planthoppers-and-leafhoppers/-->
    </string>
    <string name="glf_pesticide">
        LAMDAXIN 2.5 EC \nAGRO CYPERMETHRIN 5 EC \nPHENOM 50 EC
    </string>
    <string name="glf_activeI">
       LAMBDA‐CYHALOTHRIN \nCYPERMETHRIN  \nPHENTHOATE
    </string>

    <string name="glf_mngmnt">
        • Use GLH-resistant and tungro-resistant varieties. Contact your local agriculture office for an up-to-date list of available varieties.
      \n• Reduce the number of rice crops to two per year and synchronized crop establishment across farms reduces leafhoppers and other insect vectors.
      \n• Transplant older seedlings (>3 weeks) to reduce viral disease susceptibility transmitted by leafhoppers.
      \n• Plant early within a given planting period, particularly in the dry season to reduce the risk of insect-vector disease.
      \n• Avoid planting during the peak of GLH activity (shown by historical records) to avoid infestation. Light traps can be used to show GLH numbers.
      \n• Apply nitrogen as needed (e.g., using the Leaf Color Chart) to avoid contributing to population outbreaks by applying too much nitrogen, or hindering plant recovery from planthopper damage by applying insufficient nitrogen.
      \n• Control weeds in the field and on the bunds to remove the preferred grassy hosts of GLH and promotes crop vigor.
      \n• Perform crop rotation with a non-rice crop during the dry season to decrease alternate hosts for diseases.
      \n• Intercrop upland rice with soybean to reduce the incidence of leafhoppers on rice.
      \nIn areas without tungro source, insecticides are not needed, avoid spraying of insecticide (it is often unable to prevent or reduce tungro infections).
      \nEncourage biological control agents: small wasps (parasitize the eggs), mirid bug; strepsipterans, small wasps, pipunculid flies, and nematodes (parasitize both the nymphs and adults), aquatic veliid bugs, nabid bugs, empid flies, damselflies, dragonflies, and spiders, fungal pathogen (attacks both nymph and adult).
        <!--http://www.knowledgebank.irri.org/training/fact-sheets/pest-management/insects/item/green-leafhopper-->
    </string>
 -------------------------------------------------<!--Rice Bug-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="rb_name">Rice Bug</string>
    <string name="rb_sci">Leptocorisa acuta</string>
    <string name="rb_lifeCycle">Young nymphs are green while adults are greenish‐brown. When the
                                \ntemperature is high, and the insects are not feeding, they
                                \ncamouflage themselves on the plant by taking up a particular
                                \nposture.
                                \nAdults longevity is 30‐50 days, although reports of 110‐115 days
                                \nwhen reared individually. Mating starts 7‐14 days after becoming
                                \nadult. Pre‐oviposition period is within 3‐4 days. Eggs hatch in 5‐8
                                \ndays
                                \nA female lays 200‐300 eggs in batches of 10‐20 eggs. Females rest
                                \non grassy areas and the base of the plant during sunlight.
                                <!--https://www.pinoyrice.com/wp-content/uploads/rice-bug.pdf-->
    </string>
    <string name="rb_dmg">Adults and nymphs appear in the young crop with the early rains.
            They suck sap from the developing grains at the milky stage.  All soft
            milky grains are susceptible to attack. Panicles in heavily infested
            fields remain erect.  Insect attack results in discolored or shriveled
            grains; off‐smell of raw and cooked rice, and off‐flavor of straws,
            which is unattractive to cattle.  Prior to grain formation, the bugs
            feed on succulent shoots and leaves.  Nymphs cause more damage
            than adults.
            </string>
    <string name="rb_pesticide">LAMDAXIN 2.5 EC \nTRUGOLD 60 EC \nSUPERSMAK 50 EC</string>
    <string name="rb_activeI">LAMBDA-CYHALOTHRIN 25 g/L \nDIAZINON 600 g/L \nN CYPERMETHRIn 50g/L</string>
    <string name="rb_mngmnt">Cultural
                            \n• Eliminate grassy weeds from rice fields, levees, and surrounding areas by either cutting or
                            burning to reduce habitats for egg‐laying.
                            \n• Avoid staggered planting of fields in the area to break continuous food source.
                            \n• Smoking the field by burning straw windward, and passing baskets or bags coated on the inside
                            with sticky material are promising in repelling/capturing them.
                            \n• Netting and handpicking bugs reduce their numbers.
                            \n• Put attractants such as arasan or anything with bad odor like dead snails or rats. The bugs that
                            are gathered around the attractants can be burned or sprayed with chemicals to reduce their
                            numbers.
                            \n• Awned varieties are resistant
                            \n• Varieties with panicles enclosed in the leaf sheath for longer time offer some mechanical
                            resistance to feeding.
                            \n
                            \nBiological
                            \n• Small wasps and long‐horned grasshoppers kill eggs.
                            \n• Fungal pathogens infect nymphs and adults.
                            \n•Spiders, crickets, lady beetles, and long‐horned grasshoppers feed on nymphs and adults.  </string>

    -------------------------------------------------<!--Rice Black Bug-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="rbb_name">Rice Black Bug</string>
    <string name="rbb_sci">Oryza sativa</string>
    <string name="rbb_lifeCycle">
        Female RBB deposits its eggs usually on the decaying outermost leaf sheaths on the basal part of the plants,
        although some are laid on the lower part of the leaves.
        \n The eggs are laid in mass of 40‐60 eggs, with one egg measuring to 1 mm long.
        \n A single female RBB can lay about 200 eggs during its lifetime.  The eggs hatched 5‐7 days and become a full‐
        grown adult after six weeks.
        \n Adult RBB is oval‐shaped and measures about 8‐9 mm long
    </string>
    <string name="rbb_dmg">
        • “Deadheart” – A condition of the plant wherein the damaged tillers’ center leaves turn brown and die.  This
damage occurs when the infestation happens during the tillering stage.
        \n• Panicles with empty grains or underdeveloped panicles.  This damage occurs when the infestation happens
during the booting stage.
        \n• “Bugburn” –   A condition of the plant wherein the leaves turn reddish brown, resulting in crop loss.  This
damage occurs when the infestation happens from the seed bed, maximum tillering up to harvesting stage.</string>
    <string name="rbb_pesticide">NIMBECIDINE \nCHIX 2.5 EC \nDECIS 2.5 EC</string>
    <string name="rbb_activeI">DELTAMETHRIN 25 g/L \nBETA-CYPERMETHRIN 25 g/L \nAZADIRACHTIN 3g/L</string>
    <string name="rbb_mngmnt">Integrated Management of Rice Black Bug
        \n1. Grow Rice Black Bug (RBB)‐tolerant varieties.
        \nUse tolerant varieties such as IR 1314, IR 44526, and
        IR 10871‐75‐3‐2‐2 to minimize yield loss from RBB
        attacks.  Grow these only in areas where tungro is
        not a problem because these varieties are highly
        susceptible to tungro.
        \n2. Plant early‐maturing varieties during the regular planting time in the community.
        \nSynchronous planting must be made over large contiguous areas, preferably over a 1 km radius within a
        locality. This is to evade the damaging population levels of RBB and to break its life cycle.
        \n3. Conserve and augment natural enemies of RBB.
        \nConserve natural enemies of RBB by not using chemicals that will kill them. Augment natural enemies of RBB
        by introducing parasitoids and pathogens in areas where they are not present.
        \n4. Weed control (sanitation).
        \nControl weeds to remove alternate hosts that serve as breeding sites for RBB.
        \n5. Use trap crop.
        \nEssentially, a trap crop is a small planting of a crop that is more attractive to RBB than the crop to be
        protected. Use this to divert colonizing individuals of RBB to a trap crop where they can be destroyed.
        \n6. Plow immediately after harvest.
        \nAll stages of RBB are present on rice stubbles, thus incorporating the stubbles into the soil destroys their
        breeding/hiding habitat.
        \n7. Flood the field.
        \nTo determine whether RBB eggs are parasitized or not, collect about 5 egg masses and place them inside a
        container. Cover the mouth of the container with a nylon mesh and wait for about a week for parasitoids
        (wasps) to emerge. If no wasps emerge, flood the area.
        \n8. Release ducks in rice fields.
        \nDucks eat RBB and other pests so release them in an
        insecticide‐free rice fields with standing water about a month
        after transplanting up to heading.
        \n9. Apply metarhizium anisopliae
        \nhttps://www.pinoyrice.com/wp-content/uploads/rice-black-bug.pdf</string>

    -------------------------------------------------<!--Rice Grain Bug-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="rgb_name">Rice Grain Bug</string>
    <string name="rgb_sci"> Paraeuscosmetus pallicomis</string>
    <string name="rgb_lifeCycle">Female RGB [lay] their eggs singly; [these are] whitish or transparent in color…then
        [these turn] reddish to brown upon hatching.
        [A] newly emerged adult is light green to orange, while [a] fully developed adult [turns from] light brown to black
        in color and when disturbed or alarmed, hides among leaves, panicles, stubbles, and crevices…They can be seen walking
        or crawling, then [they] climb up and [go] down repeatedly from one rice [stubble] to another. It usually appears when
        the temperature becomes hotter, usually from 9 a.m. to 4 p.m., and [they can] be hardly found during [the] cool times
        of the day.</string>
    <string name="rgb_dmg"> RGB damage rice by sucking out the contents of developing grains from pre-flowering spikelets
        to soft dough stage resulting [in] unfilled or empty grains and discoloration…Immature and adult rice grain bugs
        both feed on rice grains.</string>
    <string name="rgb_pesticide">LAMDAXIN 2.5 EC \nAGRO CYPERMETHRIN 5 EC \nTRUGOLD 60 EC</string>
    <string name="rgb_activeI">LAMBDA-CYHALOTHRIN 25 g/L \nN CYPERMETHRIN 50g/L \nDIAZINON 600 g/L</string>
    <string name="rgb_mngmnt">
        The land preparation is crucial in controlling the spread of the bug. RGB lays
        egg under the soil, and intensive plowing exposes their eggs to the sun, causing [these] to…[spoil, thus arresting]
        the insect’s growth. To preserve standing crops, especially those in the vegetative stage, farmers are advised to
        flood or soak the field for at least 10 hours to…spoil the eggs so [these cannot] hatch.
        \nSynchronous planting can help avoid [the] overlapping of [incidences] of insect population and disease occurrence.
        Harvesting at the same would enable farmers to observe the same fallow period (leaving the field idle for 30 days),
        which breaks [the] pest cycle and [destroys] its hosts.
<!--    source: https://www.agriculture.com.ph/2017/12/30/debugging-the-rice-grain-bug/-->
    </string>

    -------------------------------------------------<!--Leaffolder-->----------------------------------------------------
    <string name="lf_name">Leaffolder</string>
    <string name="lf_sci"> Cnaphalocrocis medinalis</string>
    <string name="lf_lifeCycle"> The adult rice leaffolder is a yellow-brown moth. Leaffolder caterpillars fold the rice leaves around
            themselves and attach the leaf margins together with silk strands. Each female lays around 300 eggs at
            night during a lifecycle of three to 10 days. Larvae are yellow, turn yellowish‐green with brown heads as
            they mature, and are about 12‐25 mm long. Each larva can make two to four folded leaves. Pupa is about
            9-12 mm long and is found inside the rolled leaf. Adults are yellow brown in color. Adults usually emerge in
            the evening. Females lay eggs at night.
<!--        https://pdf.usaid.gov/pdf_docs/PA00K8XK.pdf-->
</string>
    <string name="lf_dmg"> Leaffolder caterpillars fold a rice leaf around themselves and attach the leaf margins together with silk strands.
        They feed inside the folded leaf creating longitudinal white and transparent streaks on the blade.</string>
    <string name="lf_pesticide">TREBON 10 EC \nSUNO CYPERMETHRIN 5 EC \nTRUGOLD 60 EC</string>
    <string name="lf_activeI">ETOFENPROX 25g/L \nCYPERMETHRIN 55 g/L n\DIAZINON 600g/L</string>
    <string name="lf_mngmnt">
        To prevent leaffolder outbreaks:
        \n• Use resistant varieties.
        \n• Contact your local agriculture office for an up-to-date list of available varieties.
        \n• Follow rice with a different crop, or fallow period.
        \n• Avoid ratooning.
        \n• Flood and plow field after harvesting if possible.
        \n• Remove grassy weeds from fields and borders.
        \n• Reduce density of planting.
        \n• Use balanced fertilizer rates.
        \n• Spraying pesticides is not advisable during early crop stages.
        \nMany farmers in Asia lack the necessary safety equipment and expertise
        to use pesticides safely and therefore should not use them. See a crop
        protection specialist for guidance specific to your situation.
<!--    http://www.knowledgebank.irri.org/training/fact-sheets/pest-management/insects/item/rice-leaffolder-->
    </string>
</resources>